So what is a Standardised Operating Procedure?
A Standardised Operating Procedure, or SOP, is
a documented set of instructions that outlines
how to complete a specific task or process.
SOP are commonly used in various industries,
including manufacturing, healthcare, and
food service, to ensure that tasks are
completed consistently and efficiently.
A SOP typically includes a clear and
concise description of the task or
process, a list of necessary materials and
equipment, step by step instructions, safety
precautions, and quality control measures.
These instructions provide employees with
a detailed roadmap of how to complete a
task or process, reducing the likelihood
of errors and increasing efficiency.
Let's take a look at an example
SOP and what it should include.
In this example, we will look at a
SOP for a busy restaurant kitchen.
So this is the SOP for the kitchen at Blue's
Restaurant, and as you can see, the first
thing it has on is the SOP number, the
title, which is Blue's Restaurant Kitchen.
And then we have who wrote the
SOP, and that was the head chef.
It was reviewed by the kitchen manager, and
it was authorised by the restaurant manager.
Each person signs the document and they also
add the date that they signed off that document.
You also have the effective date, which is from
when the SOP is effective from, and the review
date, the scheduled review date, which is a year
in advance of the actual first effective date.
You then also have the people who work
in the kitchen who are required to read
that and confirm that they've read it.
So if there are any errors or any
mishaps or anything goes wrong, you can
confirm who has read it and who has not.
You then come down to the
actual main body of content.
This is the purpose of the SOP, which
is to maintain a clean, tidy and safe
kitchen environment in order to promote
food safety and prevent accidents.
The scope of the SOP, this applies to all
staff members who work in the kitchen, who's
responsible for what, and then we come to the
actual procedures which covers personal hygiene,
cleaning and sanitizing surfaces, proper
storage of food and supplies, disposal of waste,
cleaning and maintenance of equipment, pest
control, the cleaning schedule and training.
So everything that's included in this
procedure is there primarily to ensure the
safe and effective operation of the kitchen.
So there's no health hazards, there's no
risks to food contamination and everybody
is aware of what they need to do.
So if you came in and you were just
starting in the business, you would read
the SOP and you should fully understand
exactly what you need to do at all times.
You also have the opportunity
to review or make changes.
So an SOP is not necessarily set in stone.
If there is an opportunity for changes,
or if changes are required due to changes
in legislation or working practices, you
can then make the changes to that SOP.
But they need to be recorded.
So what you would do is add the new SOP
number, the effective date, what changes
were made, and the previous SOP number.
So this would then change to SOP number
two, when it was effective from what
has been done to change it, and then you
would make reference to SOP number one.
So this has given you a full audit trail of
the SOP from start, and how it has developed
or changed to the current and existing SOP.